Guide to the Nicholas J. Hoff Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Nicholas J. Hoff papers
1903-1997
1940-1997
SC0883
Hoff, Nicholas J. (Nicholas John), 1906-
5 Linear feet
Collection includes articles and papers by Hoff on aircraft structures and other matters, 1944-1981; diplomas, awards and other biographical materials, 1928-1997; and materials he collected on the history of aviation including articles, reports, and photographs, 1903-1958.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Nicholas J. Hoff was a professor emeritus of aeronautics and astronautics at Stanford University at the time of his death in 1997. Born on Jan. 3, 1906 in the small town of Magyarovar in western Hungary, he came to Stanford in 1939 for graduate work and earned his Ph.D. in 1942. He taught at the Polytechnic Institute in Brooklyn before returning to Stanford in 1957 to start an independent department of aeronautical engineering. In 1965 he published a famous textbook titled "The Analysis of Structures." Although his focus was primarily on aeronautical structures, much of his work was extremely general and has been applied in a number of different fields.
Description of the Collection
Collection includes articles and papers by Hoff on aircraft structures and other matters, 1944-1981; diplomas, awards and other biographical materials, 1928-1997; and materials he collected on the history of aviation including articles, reports, and photographs, 1903-1958.
Access Terms
Hoff, Nicholas J. (Nicholas John), 1906-; Aeronautics.; Airframes.; Airplanes--Design and construction.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2007-290
  - Failure Analysis Associates I.O.U. to SU School of Engineering (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Die Eidgenössiche Technische Hochschule, Zürich (Diploma) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - ASME medal - extra (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ASME medal - photographs (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ASME medal & Hon. Member - Slides (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - “Stanford on the Job: Aviation Industry” (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memorial Church and Faculty Club for 10/23/97: Memorial (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Vivian Church Hoff memorial cards (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - History 10: History of Western Civilization syllabus, Stanford (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Diploma (Latin and Hungarian): A Magyar Tudományos (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The New York Academy of Sciences 166th Annual Meeting (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - New York Academy of Sciences 1983 I.B. Laskowitz Award (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Groups at Conference on Naval Strcs. (photos) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - bound correspondence 1970-71 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bending and Buckling of Rectangular Sandwich Plates (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Idealized Columns (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Some Recent Studies of the Buckling of Thin Shells (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - A Strain Energy Derivation of the Torsional – Flexural Buckling (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - A Study of the Accuracy of the Geckeler Approximation (1961) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Applied Mechanics and Aeronautics in Japan (1964) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mechanics Applied to Creep Testing (1958) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Creep Buckling (1956, 1969) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Structures and Materials for Finite Lifetime (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Reversed Creep (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Creep Buckling of Circular Cylindrical Shells in Pure Bending (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Buckling at High Temperature (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Rules and Methods of Stress and Stability Calculations in the (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Mechanics Applied to Creep Testing (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - On the Transition from Asymmetric to Multilobed Creep Buckling (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Creep Buckling of Plates and Shells (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Creep Buckling articles to do with stress, behaviors, and experiments (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Thin-walled circular cylinder articles (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hoff’s Problem in a Probabilistic Setting, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Stress Concentrations in Cylindrically Orthotropic Composite Plates with a Circular Hole, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - A Survey of the Theories of Creep Buckling, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Flier and Designer: Jacob Christian Ellehammer, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Experimental Study of Pressure Vessel Models Having Fabrication Flaws (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Rules and Methods of Stress and Stability Calculations in the Presence of Creep, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Creep Buckling: Two papers from 1968 and 1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Three papers on thin-walled circular cylindrical shells, 1969 & ‘71 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, Report 934, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Article in Cyrillic typeset (ЯВЛЕНИЕ ПОЛЗУЧЕСТИ) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Russian (?) article (ВЛИЯНИЕ МЕРИДИАННОЙ КРИВИЗНЫ, НА КОЭФФИЦИЕНТЫ…) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Japanese article by Hoff: The Effects of Temperature and Time on Aircraft and Missile Structures (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Buckling and Stability, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - High Temperature Structures, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Aerostructures: Selected Papers of Nicholas J. Hoff (bound, volume) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Stress Distribution in the Presence of Steady Creep (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Philosophy of Safety in the Supersonic Age (1956) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Dynamic Analysis of the Buckling of Laterally Loaded Flat Arches, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Applied Mechanics and Aeronautics in Japan, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Creep Deformations of Rectangular Frames, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Buckling of a Thin-Walled Circular Cylindrical Shell Heated Along an Axial Strip (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - The Perplexing Behavior of Thin Circular Cylindrical Shells in Axial Compression, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Selection of Numerical Coefficient in Shell Buckling Formula (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The Applicability of Saint-Venant’s Principle to Airplane Structures, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Some Structural Problems of Space Flight, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Space Travel – How and Why, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - AIAA Distinguished Lecture Series (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Thermal Barrier - Structures (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Structural Stability, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Creep in Metal Structures, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Structural Effects of Aerodynamic Heating, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Structural Stability, correspondence, and unidentified photo (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Notes on High Temperature Effects in Structures (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Notes on High Temperature Effects in Structures (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Notes (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Honolulu Paper (Also Stanford) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Rules and Methods of Stress and Stability Calculations in the Presence of Creep, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Essays on Buckling and Creep (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Computer Algorithms for Solving Non-Linear Problems, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Dynamic Stability of Structures, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Papers on thin circular cylindrical or spherical shells (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Papers on creep (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - List of Pibal Reports, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Creep Deformations of Rectangular Frames, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - A Theoretical and Experimental Investigation of Creep Buckling, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Short papers on stress, structures, and temperature effects on speed and structure (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - IUTAM United States National Committee / Theoretical and Applied Mechanics 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - DC-10: Stresses in Airplane Cabin Floors and related correspondence; Letters to the Editor re: DC-10 doors (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Thin-walled Monocoques (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Creep Buckling (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Remarks on the Buckled Shapes of Thin-walled Circular Cylindrical and Conical Shells (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - “What is Creep?” and “Short Cuts in Creep Buckling Analysis” (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Buckling and Stability (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Composite Materials in Aircraft Structures (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Axially Symmetric Creep Buckling of Circular Cylindrical Shells in Axial Compression (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Buckling of Thin Cylindrical Shell under Hoop Stresses Varying in Axial Direction (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Creep Buckling of Plates and Shells (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Influence Coefficients for Filament-wound Shells (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Elastic Analysis of Motor Case Shells (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Transmission of an Axial Load from a Cylindrical Shell to a Spherical Shell (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - A Non-Linear Model Study of the Thermal Buckling of Thin Elastic Shells (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Structures and Materials for Finite Lifetime (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Dynamic Stability of Structures (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Some Structural Problems of Space Flight (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - articles on airplane structures (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Structural Problems of Future Aircraft (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Course Content in Aircraft Structures (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - The Applicability of Saint-Venant’s Principle to Airplane Structures (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - The Proportioning of Aircraft Frameworks (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Philosophy of Safety in the Supersonic Age (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Axially Symmetric Creep Buckling of Circular Cylindrical Shells in Axial Compression (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - The Necking and the Rupture of Rods Subjected to Constant Tensile Loads (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Structures and High Temperatures (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - The Structural Effects of Aerodynamic Heating (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Structures for High Speed (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Bending and Buckling of Rectangular Sandwich Plates (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Innovation in Aircraft Structures – Fifty Years Ago and Today (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - American Aviation Historical Society Journal, vol. 23, no. 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - “Papers of Wilbur and Orville Wright” (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Thin Shells in Aerospace Structures (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Deformation of an Inflated Circular Cylindrical Membrane by a Uniform Radial Line Load (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - General Formulas for Influence Coefficients of Thin Spherical Shells (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - A Graphic Resolution of Strain (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Thin Circular Conical Shells Under Arbitrary Loads (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Snapping of Imperfect Thin-Walled Circular Cylindrical Shells of Finite Length (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - The Idealized Column (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Elastically Encased Struts (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The Development of a Technique for Testing Stiff Panels in Edgewise Compression (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Recent Progress in Applied Mechanics (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Thermal Effects in Structures (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Graduate and Research Work in Universities and the Use of College Men in Industry and Government (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Mechanics Applied to Creep Testing: William M. Murray Lecture (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Concentrated Load Effects in Reinforced Monocoque Structures (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Shortcuts in Creep Buckling Analysis (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Stress Analysis of Rings for Monocoque Fuselages (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - A Numerical Procedure for the Calculation of the Moments in Edge Reinforcements of Cutouts in Monocoques (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Stresses in a Reinforced Monocoque Cylinder Under Concentrated Symmetric Transverse Loads (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Instability of Monocoque Structures in Pure Bending (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Stresses in Space-Curved Rings Reinforcing the Edges of Cut-Outs in Monocoque Fuselages (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - General Instability of Monocoque Cylinders (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - On the Transition from Axisymmetric to Multilobed Creep Buckling (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Creep Buckling of Rectangular Plates under Uniaxial Compression (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Stress Distribution in the Presence of Creep (3 articles) (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Articles on stress concentrations in cylindrically orthotropic plates (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Low Buckling Stresses of Axially Compressed Circular Cylindrical Shells of Finite Length (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - The Effect of Creep on the Stress Distribution in Structures (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - A Strain Energy Derivation of the Torsional-Flexural Buckling Loads of Straight Columns of Thin-Walled Open Sections (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Stress Analysis of Aircraft Frameworks (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Creep in Metal Structures (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Approximate Analysis of Structures in Presence of Moderately Large Creep Deformations (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Reversed Creep: A Remark to the Creep Buckling Theory of Rabotnov and Shesterikov (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Rules and Methods of Stress and Stability Calculations in the Presence of Creep (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Buckling and Stability: 41st Wilbur Wright Memorial Lecture (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Mechanics Applied to Creep Testing (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Some Recent Studies of the Buckling of Thin Shells (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Buckling at High Temperature (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Two articles on Thermal Buckling (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Rapid Creep in Structures (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Buckling of Sandwich-type Panels (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Approximate Analysis of Structures in the Presence of Moderately Large Creep Deformations (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - The Structural Effects of Aerodynamic Heating (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - What is Creep? (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Damping of the Vibrations of a Coiled Spring Due to Creep (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Dynamic Criteria of Buckling (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - The Dynamics of the Buckling of Elastic Columns (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Rapid Creep in Structures (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Stable and Unstable Equilibrium of Plane Frameworks (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - A Survey of the Theories of Creep Buckling (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Kinematically Unstable Space Frameworks (2 copies) (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Buckling of Thin Shells (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - The Perplexing Behavior of Thin Circular Cylindrical Shells in Axial Compression (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Inelastic Buckling of Columns in the Conventional Testing, Machine (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Low Buckling Stresses of Axially Compressed Circular Cylindrical Shells of Finite Length - Corrected (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Some Recent Studies of the Buckling of Thin Shells (revised) (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - A New Solution of the Buckling Problem of Thin Circular Cylindrical Shells Heated Along an Axial Strip (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - 0
  - A Variational Development of the Governing Equations and Boundary Conditions for Sandwich Plates With Ideally-Orthotropic Cores and an Application to the Interaction of General and Local Instability Under Axial Compression (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - The Deformation of an Inflated Circular Cylindrical Membrane by a Uniform Radial Line Load (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Buckling of Axially Compressed Circular Cylindrical Shells at Stresses Smaller than the Classical Critical Value (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Dynamic Stability of Structures (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - On the Transition from Axisymmetric to Multilobed Creep Buckling (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Short Cuts in Creep Buckling Analysis (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Rules and Methods of Stress and Stability Calculations in the Presence of Creep (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Dynamic Stability of Structures (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Some Structural Problems of Space Flight (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - A Non-Linear Model Study of the Thermal Buckling of Thin Elastic Shells (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Structures and Materials for Finite Lifetime (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Buckling of Circular Cylindrical Shells in Axial Compression (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Lower Bounds for the Buckling Pressure of Spherical Shells (revised) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Creep Buckling of Rectangular Plates Under Uniaxial Compression (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Mechanics Applied to Creep Testing (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Diplom-Arbeit 1928 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Institut de France: Academie des Sciences, Extrait du Decret 1989 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - George Washington University School of Engineering and Applied Science Certificate of Recognition (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Of Planes, Planebuilders, and Pilots: Contents and Chapters 1-2 (plus pg. 1 of Chapter 3) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Of Planes, Planebuilders, and Pilots: Chapters 3-4 (plus pg. 1 of Chapter 5) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Of Planes, Planebuilders, and Pilots: Chapter 5 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Of Planes, Planebuilders, and Pilots: Chapter 6-end (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Description of Blue Streak Structure with Photographs, Aug. 1906 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Bristol, Filton House: Photos (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - New York Times: Aviation Section, October 11, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - The Times: Survey of British Aviation, 1953, 1957, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Photos: Smirnoff Sailplane Derby Racing Information (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Misc. photos (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Bristol (photos) (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Photos: Aviation misc. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Photos: Figures for Chapter 3 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Montgomery: Photos (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - April 22, 1946 Daily News: New York – Washington Flight: 29 minutes (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Photos from Saab (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Santos Dumont VVIA Ellehammer Chapter 1 (photos) (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Douglas Commercial Air Transports (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - J.C.H. Ellehammer – Autographed photograph album (some loose photos) (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Photos – negatives? (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Photo #6 from top of present “Montgomery Hill,” 1911 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Illustrations/Figures (photos) (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Photos from Short Brothers and Harland Ltd., Queen’s Island, Belfast (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Innovation Photos (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Curtiss (photos) (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Smithsonian (photos) (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Heinkel (photos) (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Reissner Ente (photos) (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - miscellaneous photos, 1903-1913 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Vickers Vimy Geodetic (photos) (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Courtesy of Aireview, Japan (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - 562 and 531 (photos) (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Pages from album (photos) (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Monoscope (photos) (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous (photos) (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Hawker Siddeley (photos) (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - De Havilland 287 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Cessna (photos) (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Dassault (photos) (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Royal Aeronautical Society (photos) (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Rotter Lajos T.H. Lin Chunkng Plane (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Looking Inside - photos (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Innovation in Aircraft Structures (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous photos 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous photos 3 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Concorde/Staaken (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Northrop Alpha (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Chapter 7 (photos) (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Hawker-Siddeley (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Photos of Kármán Lecture (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - First batch of Smithsonian photos (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Torsion Tests of 17 Skydyne Test Specimens (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Photos from Russia (Box 10, Folder 12)